I'm called go live. Now we wait.
A little [snorts] bit until it starts
and then we'll do it.
Hello and welcome back to an interview
today of by Tesla coming to you live
from
Focus 2026.
John is my next guest. Welcome John.
>> Thank you.
>> And John, so your your topic is
locally basically running on the AI
models and this kind of stuff.
So let me ask you.
They're not very good, are they?
The local models.
>> That's controversial.
>> Okay. [laughter]
>> No, abs-
absolutely no, you're you're wrong. They
are incredibly good. Today's um
I have models running on my phone that
are better than Chat GPT from last year,
1 year ago. I have models running on my
laptop that are better than Chat GPT and
um the the best models in the world and
and I use Chat GPT as an example, but
Claude Sonnet and Opus um as of November
last year. That's 6 months back.
>> Okay, so well it's still 6 months back.
We are now the frontier models now are 6
months better.
>> Okay, so if you're if you're writing
code,
uh absolutely. Um
They've the frontier models, however,
if you're writing code and um it's
generic- working on code, it doesn't
have to be running on your laptop. You
can still use the the GLM 5.1s, you can
use the Kimiko 2.6. Um you can use um
mini LLM mini LM
um
M2.7,
and you can run um DeepSeek V4.
They're all open source. They're all
open weights or open weights, I should
say rather than open source. And while
you can't run them on your laptop, you
can still run them in anyone's
environment that has that. And
>> And and still we will have mostly So,
the advantages are are mostly cost. Or
are there others?
Especially if you are not trying any
more
>> Okay, so let's just put them to If
you're running the the the the four that
I just mentioned, um yes, cost is a big
thing. You're looking at about a 20th of
the cost. So, if you're running through
some sort of general coding stuff that
doesn't need to go out to your
customers, I run mine mine sit and run
all night numerous laptops and machines
around the company. We're running on
Kimiko 2.6 most of the time. Um And
these models, by the time the video
comes out, will be out of date by cuz
they they change on a weekly, you know,
basis, literally. Um but if you're
running um models on your local machine,
there are
um
they'll run pretty good for coding, but
I didn't use them for coding. I mean,
there are so many other things you can
run them on.
>> Yeah, and that makes sense. So, so yeah,
so obviously price is is is a very big
factor, especially considering how the
frontier models are getting more and
more expensive almost every day. So,
that's a good alternative. Um
let me ask you, how do I know
that you know, I'm spoiled by all this
fake subsidized token economy, and I'm
like, "Hey, I'm used to run the frontier
models for 10 bucks a month."
Now suddenly that's not the case, and I
have this formal that if I'm going to
run local models, I won't get the same
results what I need. How do I know for
what the local models are good enough
for me, so I won't have to compromise on
quality?
>> Okay. So, let's if we can just break
slightly from coding. Um coding is one
of the most uh demanding tasks in in
this um so
if we're going to concentrate on coding,
then you need really the latest, most
powerful models because you're competing
against everyone else and and they're
all going to be a couple of weeks behind
you. You you want to be able to But if
you're running you're running rag,
you're running um you're going through
your emails, you're going through other
people's emails, you're you're running
um
text to image, image to text, text to
speech, speech to text um as will be
transcoded by this very video, etc. All
those models run 100% as good as and in
many cases better and faster locally
than they run in the cloud.
>> How about uh text authoring? How about
um like um general reasoning?
>> Two different things you mentioned
there.
Yeah.
>> the two different examples. Yeah.
>> Text text authoring, I don't think any
models are brilliant at text authoring.
Models read really well. They read you
know
very significantly better than they
write. Um same as
uh
no disrespect, but when you speak
English, I can tell immediate you you
understand English fluently 100%.
>> Yeah.
>> Um but you don't speak it the same and
so just as a model you a model can read
and it reads beautifully well and it it
it uh but they don't write particularly
well. Um
for reasoning, the even the small models
running on the machines are really
really good and certainly for for going
through PDFs, for trans- transposing,
for reading multiple languages, for
decomposing photos, pictures,
as good as if not in many cases been
proven to be better than the um
proprietary models.
>> Interesting. So, okay. So so coding
aside, another very, I would say, a hot
right now are all the personal
assistants all the clothes for different
different flavors.
I think
they are a very good candidate for
switching from cloud frontier
subscription models to to those both
because they run 24/7 so they burn
through a lot of tokens but also because
those models are good enough for what
they are doing.
>> Totally. I mean you should always be
looking for the most efficient cheapest
and fastest model to do the job that you
need to do. And if you're
downloading video trans- transcoding it
translating it um
basically looking for information in in
that then the local models literally run
on a phone today will do that. We use
them for we go into a meeting they're
busy picking up all the information
and and basically busy processing it.
>> Yeah, so so basically your personal
assistant they go through your emails
that you know look at your calendars and
you important information prepare you
for meetings and this kind of stuff.
This is all
>> And and and let's get to one of the most
important parts privacy. A local model
is not by definition on its own is is is
totally private but you can certainly
make it private. If it sits on your
phone or it sits on your laptop
you can be off the internet and if
you're recording a conversation it is
totally yours. We we're living in Europe
and it's um
privacy is important here.
>> Yeah, and that all kind of stuff and all
this kind of stuff.
>> I mean you use one of these American
things that's all been everything's been
taken off and using for training and
before you know it it's uh it's
published on the internet whatever it
was.
>> That's very true. That's very true. All
right, okay. So rule of thumb when do we
start looking at something that other
than frontier subscription models?
>> I would suggest everything except coding
and coding unless you've got the sort of
top of the range latest 128 gigabyte Mac
everything but coding, but literally
everything. Everything we run is local.
>> Brilliant. Okay. So,
I don't know what do you folks but
for me that's kind of a very
I would say
revolutionary concept. I mean I assume
that the local models can do some stuff,
but what you are saying is
really interesting and I will definitely
give it a try for for more than I would
do
>> You're going to get lower latency.
You're going to get faster inference out
of a small Quen 3.5 4B model than you
will out of ChatGPT.
>> Well, that's that's very impressive.
John, thank you very much.
>> Thank you.
>> You stay tuned for one more interview of
Yianni in the video by Tessal at AI
Focus right after this.
Perfect. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Yep.
>> [music]
>> Sorry for being a little bit dramatic
but I think